Keep quiet now.
That's it, I'm already gone.
CARJA OUTLANDER: By the Sun, I'm alive! Thank you, Nora.
CARJA OUTLANDER: You, please, can we talk?
ALOY: This will do nicely.
CARJA OUTLANDER: You saved me. Will you accept this as thanks?
Calm, calm.
CARJA OUTLANDER: Follow me!
OSERAM: Carja may like this heat but I sure don't.
ALOY: They must be Oseram.
ALOY: They've put their stamp on this place.
OSERAM: Thinking about heading back to The Claim.
OSERAM: Look, I've got a pair of sturdy Oseram hands,
and I know how to put them to use. There'll always be work for me.
ALOY: Someone over there?
Well, well.
Always told Dervahl a woman would undo him, and he had it coming.
Ha! I've calluses older than you.
I have calluses enough if you wanna test me.
Ha, she sparks!
I believe it, flamehair.
Petra Forgewoman.
Aaah, Aloy … machine hunter.
Mmm, machine hunter, eh?
Huh, I could have a use for you.
Straight of it is we're being muscled out of our own claim.
That's why I've been working on this scrap-spitting beast.
It's a dispute settler.
I've never seen anything like it.
Your design?
Mmm, see my face in it, can you?
This one's mother helped reclaim Meridian back in the day.
A job like that isn't done with strategy.
They needed to shake the walls,
turn the Mad Sun King's army to blood and feathers.
What's that face for?
Weapons with such power.
It's not the weapon, flamehair, it's the wielder.
If that siege had touched the great elevator, they'd have answered to me.
Good work, that elevator. Story in every chain link.
I'll make you suffer them one day, if you like.
This beast doesn't have a story yet.
Too heavy to carry, eats metal like a Snapmaw.
What is this place, Petra?
The Free Heap.
Free, because we answer to no-one but ourselves,
the metal, and the dust storms.
And the heap's back there.
A scrapyard, piled by Oseram past from the leavings of the Old Ones.
Breathe it in, get the smell in you.
Smoke, and sweat.
Living in the trees has dulled your senses.
I could taste five medals just in my spit.
So all this scrap was left by the ancients. Was it a battlefield?
Mmm, stockpile maybe, or a rubbish heap.
Packed so tight it all fused together.
Those Old Ones tossed away more than we'll ever know.
But don't you want to know? To understand what it all meant?
Nah. Some delvers spend their whole lives trying to make sense of it, not me.
What it means is there's good smelting here.
Yeah, don't need to understand a forest to chop down the trees for your arrows.
If you did, you'd know Ridge-Wood makes better shafts.
Oh, careful, you'll scald your tongue with that fire.
I don't pine for the Old Ones.
They had their time, their works are finished.
All their inventions are under mountains now, rust on bones.
My sisters and brothers of the forge will make a new world.
You run the forge and the town too?
The town is the forge! And everyone pulls their weight.
The right way to do it, without all the ealdormen having their say.
If we were back in The Claim — Oseram land —
three days argument any time someone wants to hammer in a bolt.
Sounds infuriating.
Oh, it is. But we like arguing.
You need hot air to keep a furnace burning.
Still, some traditions aren't up for debate.
I would have ended up "Petra Forgewife".
How'd you like the sound of that?
[laughs] I don't think it fits you.
Good answer.
That's why I left.
I was steel-young from the forge then.
Could make anything of myself before I cooled in my ways.
So you left your homeland and came here?
Went to Meridian, everyone does.
Joined the work gangs on the great elevator.
We finished just as the Mad King got a taste for blood.
So I spat and swore I'd find a place for everyone who stuck with me.
We lived job to job until the war ended.
Then we came upon this old Oseram camp.
Long abandoned, metal piled up high.
A place to start again, a place to leave my mark.
Ha, when I was your age, I thought the lasting mark came from the hardest strike.
I suppose you know better now that you're an elder?
Ha, trade secret.
You said you're being pushed out of your territory?
Out of the junk heap.
A pack of Scrappers came snuffling in
just after we opened a good seam of weapon parts.
And now we've got a standoff with a gang of bandits at our foundry.
They blockaded us out.
They're sitting on our power cells.
Guess they like shiny things.
Well, to finish up our defences, I need those parts and cells.
In and out job, keep your hands clean.
I'm not afraid of getting them dirty.
Ha! Aren't you a blast of air from the bellows!
OSERAM: … like it … there's a man who knows how to …
OSERAM: The longer we stay here, the more it'll feel like home.
OSERAM: Is it just me or do the Carja people walk slow?
Don't they have places to be?
OSERAM: Aren't you a sight!
BANDIT: If I had right of rule, I'd have taken the town first.
More slaves for digging up lightning boxes.
BANDIT: Then make your claim for it when the others get here.
Won't be long now.
BANDIT: Whoa!
ALOY: All this scrap, dragged here from who knows where and when.
BANDIT: They're gonna wipe us out!
BANDIT: If we don't rally, we're scrap.
ALOY: Alright.
ALOY: Bandits have a good defence.
ALOY: Better spot all their sentrys before I look for the power cells.
There, a power cell.
Okay, done. Now to get into the Scrappers run and find those weapon parts.
You'll get yours when the clan blows in, town's good as torched.
Okay.
Lots of Scrappers prowling, hope they haven't stripped the parts already.
The Scrappers made that pile.
Strange, are they nesting?
Now let me find something Petra can use, fast!
Oh, mine now!
Back to Petra, I've been in this scrap yard long enough.
Petra, I have the parts you wanted but there are more bandits coming.
The rest of their clan, they want to take the town.
Do they now? Hold this thing steady while I give it a voice.
Then we'll let it talk terms for us.
Now take it up and brace yourself.
Don't press it against your hips if you ever want to use those for…
Alright, alright, I got it.
ALOY: Heavy, all I can do to hold it up.
ALOY: Come on, then, if you're coming!
BANDIT: Run this forgedirt town red, boys!
PETRA: Heh, manners!
BANDIT: At 'em, boys!
PETRA: Haha, she's working well so far!
PETRA: Room for improvement on the gun, no complaints about the gunner.
PETRA: Haha, anyone but a bandit clan would pull back now.
BANDIT: Come on, you bungheads, they only have one cannon!
PETRA: They're gathering under the bridge, Aloy, bring it down on 'em.
ALOY: What? It's your bridge.
PETRA: Bridges come and go, shoot it down.
ALOY: Oh boy.
PETRA: Whoa! Might have overdone it a little.
PETRA: Now I'm no soldier, but I'd call that a rout.
Oh, my teeth hurt from all that.
That's interesting. Need a leather strap to bite down on, perhaps.
We'll give those wretches a sky burial.
That's fancy talk for leaving them out for the birds.
More than they'd done for us if this thing didn't work.
Uh, if it didn't work? It could have not worked?!
It isn't finished, that's why we're testing it.
Now, now, you had your Nora toys to fight with.
Saying goes, "You can only trust metal."
But my trust was placed well in you.
You're owed Aloy Machinehunter. I won't forget it.
And neither will I, Petra.
ALOY: Whoa, still feel the lightning snap in my hair.
It'd be fascinating, if they weren't looking for me,
Up and go!
Damn dust, ugh!
Whoa, there.
I hunted that Thunderjaw you asked for.
I should be the one telling a story this time.
You carry it with you! Beamwire, burns, and bruises.
The salt lines of your sweat.
See, on your skin? Tiny metal flakes!
You mean it was a hard fight? How perceptive.
What signs you've shown me, huntress.
But now, the blood.
I followed red trails through a green world.
Thunderjaw, striding with the majesty of an old god.
These wicked parts, fashioned to kill men.
This great whole, made to haunt the sleep of children.
And I realise it is a young beast.
It was not there to see the first strange birds roost upon a metal skull.
It became because of us!
Hunters. I saw many, of tribes gone and yet to come.
I even saw you there, fiery haired, fierce, bared…
What?
…bared of metal, huntress.
Bared of what we tore from their hides to be strong like them, savage like them.
We build our world in the machine's shadow,
called them out with every strike of rock and hammer.
You think something — some machine — made the Thunderjaw because of us?
When you've tasted what I have, in the blood there's change.
Such a change!
It's colder than Ban-Ur, hotter than the Carja Sun!
Does any machine walk or crawl that you haven't drunk from?
In the mountains north, the Stormbirds.
Even the air in their passing crackles with potency!
In the sweep of their eyes, they see all.
Don't get too excited.
I'll get the Stormbird blood … maybe, we'll see.
They must know how the orbit slows,
fades, falls, decays, and yet returns to more than zero.
Yeah, uh-huh.
You don't fear knowledge.
You reach into its flame.
It's always an experience with you.
Learn from the machines.
Be metal-still, run blood-hot, strike lightning-quick.
Hoping they'd miss me.
Aren't you a little out of your way, Nora?
Your Sacred Lands don't extend this far.
I go where I like.